<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A short treatise of the epidemical diseases of these times communicated by a loyal pen in a letter to the Right Worshipful Sir G.B., Knight and Baronet.</title>
            <author>J. C.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 59KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B18419</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12358308</idno>
  <idno type="VID">199216</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248596528</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing C73</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">12358308</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B18419)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 199216)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 220:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A short treatise of the epidemical diseases of these times communicated by a loyal pen in a letter to the Right Worshipful Sir G.B., Knight and Baronet.</title>
                  <author>J. C.</author>
                  <author>G. B., Sir.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>30 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and are to be sold by R. Vaughan,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1662?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A satire on political and religious events.</note>
                  <note>"Licensed and published according to order"</note>
                  <note>Signed: J.C.</note>
                  <note>Date of publication from NUC pre-1956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Columbia University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Religion and politics --  England --  Anecdotes.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:199216:1"/>
            <p>A Short TREATISE Of the <hi>Epidemical Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eases</hi> of these TIMES.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Communicated by a Loyal Pen, in a Letter to the Right Worshipful</hi> Sir G. B. Knight <hi>and</hi> Baronet.</p>
            <p>Licensed and Published according to Order.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Difficilie est satyram non Scribere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed, and are to be sold by <hi>R. Vaughan,</hi> in Black-boy Court in St, <hi>Martins le Grand.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:199216:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:199216:2"/>
            <head>A Short TREATISE Of the <hi>Epidemical Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eases</hi> of these TIMES.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>LOndon</hi> hath as great a stock of <hi>jealousies</hi> and fears, as those which furnished out a war: and although the City suffers under many diseases, no one is so <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demical,</hi> as this <hi>jealous fury,</hi> or <hi>Phrenetick zeal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Reverend Bishop hath set up <hi>Lectures</hi> for a <hi>Cure,</hi> which first gave an occasion to the <hi>Disease;</hi> to try if the <hi>Monster</hi> may be kill'd by her own wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons; &amp; even some of the weapons are anointed to work a cure by <hi>Sympathy;</hi> St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church is much crowded, but it deserves an <hi>Oeodipus</hi> to resolve, whether more go out of <hi>curiosity,</hi> or <hi>devotion.</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:199216:3"/> Some say they could love that in a <hi>Tavern,</hi> which they abominate in a <hi>Church,</hi> and could be willing that the Devil only might be served in State. But it is to be hoped that what <hi>Hippocrates, Terpander</hi> and <hi>Timotheus</hi> reported of <hi>Musick</hi> in the extremity of phranticks to do Miracles; may at length be ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected in the miraculous cure of these madmen. The <hi>Musick</hi> or <hi>curiosity</hi> which brings them to Church may in time convert them, who speak of it now openly in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church, as the curious <hi>Athenians</hi> did of St. <hi>Paul, What means this babling?</hi> As yet a worse Devil then that of <hi>Saul</hi> possesseth them. That which appeased his, can only raise this, and inrage them, more then <hi>Saul</hi> ever was against <hi>David,</hi> against our princely <hi>David,</hi> because he would have God serv'd like him, with Lute, Harp and Organ.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Scurrility</hi> wanders about every part of the City, and verifies the Proverb, <hi>Qui Calvino obsequitur, calumniatorem esse oportet;</hi> he who is a Disciple to <hi>Calvin,</hi> hath took a degree in <hi>Calumny. Prejudic'd phancies</hi> may be perswaded into any thing, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as the old saw in metre, <hi>as the fool thinketh, so the Bell tinketh.</hi> A zealous man (of the society of the twang, who supplied the place of the <hi>Organ</hi> in the Church) averr'd the <hi>Organs</hi> instruments of <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneness,</hi> &amp; set up only to instruct swearing, the great ones sounding nothing but <hi>zounds, zounds,</hi> while the lesser squeak'd out, <hi>faith and troth, faith and troth.</hi> These news can make a <hi>Sister</hi> sigh at the <hi>Abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> of the prophaner age: and the <hi>Wolves</hi> in <hi>Sheeps cloathing</hi> howl themselves hoarfe by <hi>bawling</hi> against what they call <hi>Antichrist. It</hi> would be well if they could instruct them in <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Truth,</hi> and not thus
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:199216:3"/> to make the wounds of our Saviour useless, made to unite all in the bond of <hi>Faith, Truth,</hi> and <hi>Charity;</hi> so proving themselves, what a Bishop hath made them <hi>Antichrist.</hi> So far hath <hi>Church Musick</hi> been able from having the effects, ev'n that <hi>Tavern Musick</hi> hath had on the ingenuous, to be able to extasize &amp; put into fits of devotion. The <hi>Surplice, Tippet, Hood,</hi> the ornaments of <hi>Bishops, Deans,</hi> and <hi>Prebends,</hi> are all offensive, even to many of those <hi>furr'd</hi> Citizens, who for the City <hi>honour,</hi> and their <hi>own,</hi> wear <hi>Gowns, Hoods,</hi> &amp;c. And without they would make all Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies guilty of fools <hi>badges</hi> and <hi>liveries,</hi> could not easily defend their own. Thus we may guess at the <hi>madness</hi> of <hi>elapsed times,</hi> and the not more <hi>sober judgements</hi> of many in these, who could endure the <hi>Chains</hi> and <hi>Pageantry</hi> of the <hi>Major</hi> and <hi>Aldermen,</hi> not boggle at the Judges Robes, Sergeants Quoif, nor their Mr. <hi>Sermon-makers</hi> Cap, with as many seams as a Lute hath strings; yet decry the least or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nament in the <hi>Episcopal Clergie.</hi> Thus these <hi>Ada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites</hi> in understanding, who by the tasting forbidden fruit, have made some discoveries of their naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, can think the <hi>Fig-leaves</hi> of <hi>hypocrisie</hi> nearer the <hi>primitive</hi> pattern, then <hi>Aarons</hi> garments, which have <hi>Urim</hi> and <hi>Thummim perfection</hi> and <hi>light</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graven on them.</p>
            <p>Every Presbyterian Pulpit calls for a <hi>thorough Reformation,</hi> but sure it is unattainable by the half craz'd nodles of there Cock-braind <hi>Sciolists,</hi> without they can arrive to that degree of mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, as their <hi>quondam</hi> Disciples the <hi>Quakers</hi> have who like the <hi>Enthusiasis</hi> of old, have run out of their wits to entertain, what they call a Deity,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:199216:4"/> and have compleated their so long struggled for <hi>Reformation,</hi> by not onely renoucing all <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine</hi> and <hi>Disciplne</hi> in <hi>Church,</hi> but <hi>Decency</hi> and <hi>Order</hi> in <hi>State.</hi> The poor finging men in <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thedrals,</hi> give occasion to <hi>scandal.</hi> Those <hi>Surpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> which should emblemmatize <hi>innocence, Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformists</hi> report smutch'd in Alehouses, will have them divide the day betwixt God and the Devil, as if they only practised by an <hi>Anthem</hi> in the <hi>Church,</hi> to afford <hi>Belial</hi> an <hi>Orizon</hi> in a <hi>Catch,</hi> while they take their cups more devoutly, then they sing their Psalms. Some compare them to <hi>Mourners</hi> hir'd in <hi>Ireland,</hi> to howl over graves, inaffected with what they are hir'd to instruct others, will not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low them to elevate Devotion in any, whom they would teach us beleive are defective of all devotion in themselves; having no motion above <hi>Properties</hi> or <hi>Puppets,</hi> and casting their eyes like the picture of a <hi>Iack-an-Apes,</hi> moved by wire, and making a noise upon a drum in <hi>Bartholomew Fair.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the <hi>Brethren</hi> may take a more opposite and charitable resemblance from themselvs, who translated what they called <hi>Antichristian</hi> in the <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan,</hi> into their more sanctified <hi>Noses;</hi> while <hi>Hah, Haugh,</hi> and <hi>hummh,</hi> went in <hi>consort,</hi> till <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State</hi> run out into <hi>discords,</hi> indevout as these singing Men formerly, with gesticulations like <hi>Puppets</hi> and <hi>Properties, howling</hi> for hire on <hi>Fast-days,</hi> and tune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their pipes merrily on the <hi>Thanksgiving;</hi> many by talking of <hi>Religion</hi> to others, have arrived to a, degree of it in themselves, if their own professed conversion, and our charity render us not mistaken in both.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:199216:4"/>
            <p>The Reverena <hi>Bishops,</hi> like their Royal <hi>Master,</hi> do good and hear ill. These <hi>Empricks</hi> in divinity cannot be content to be <hi>paring</hi> the <hi>Corns</hi> in the <hi>feet</hi> of the <hi>Church;</hi> but they would be <hi>Pysicking</hi> of the <hi>Head.</hi> All the <hi>Rhapsodies</hi> of flaring and scurrilous <hi>phancies,</hi> the spurious issues of every <hi>idler</hi> brain in all ages, must be laid to these <hi>Fathers.</hi> Neither their Learning, Moderation, Piety, nor Power can pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail for them, nor their own dutys keep these <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cursed Sons</hi> from attempting to discover nakedness in the <hi>Fathers</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> though they discover nothing above their own cock-braind follies.</p>
            <p>Now to the great ingredients of a diurnal <hi>Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisements.</hi> There is lately printed a Book, intituled <hi>Annu Mirabilis.</hi> Wonders from Air, Earth, Water, Fire, as if all the Elements conspired to punish the wickedness of such a monstrous people, who could prefer their own liberty, a good Prince, his just right, before the <hi>Tyranny</hi> of <hi>snivelling Usurpings,</hi> and <hi>perfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious Apostates,</hi> kneaded up betwixt <hi>Dirt</hi> and <hi>Blood.</hi> As if God had no greater blessings to bestow upon a Nation, then the destruction of it by Locusts, or such vermine, which are quickned only out of the <hi>putrifaction</hi> of an <hi>intemperate Climate.</hi> The Legend takes date from <hi>August</hi> the first 60. to <hi>May</hi> 61. In this excellent and unparel'd piece (give me leave to call it so,) since it may outvie a <hi>Talmud, Alco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ran,</hi> all <hi>Popish Legends,</hi> and <hi>pious frauds:</hi> you may fine the prodigies of all ages renew'd in ours, with stories adapted to them.</p>
            <p>Here you may meet an <hi>Apotheosies,</hi> as true as that of <hi>Romulus, Iulius Caesar:</hi> Regicines are cut in pieces, like <hi>Romulus,</hi> to be deified; must be slain,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:199216:5"/> and have a star, like <hi>Iulius,</hi> attending their Limbs over <hi>Aldgate:</hi> or, as the Saints would intimate, it is such a Star guiding such Wisemen to Jesus, as can think <hi>Murder, Treason,</hi> and <hi>Hypocrisie,</hi> the only <hi>way to Heaven.</hi> Five naked men are seen in the skye. The story of their fellow Saint, Father <hi>Garnets Straw,</hi> will be shamed out of fashion. He was <hi>sainted</hi> by appearance of his shape in straw, these derive their <hi>Saint-ships</hi> no lower then by appearances in the Heavens. Mark what follows. To revenge the death of the Saints: you have <hi>Hail-stones</hi> big as <hi>Walnuts,</hi> dreadful Whirlewinds, Rivers dryed up, While Frogs and Toads are supplyed from the Air, sudden Rains, terrible Tempests, and raging Tides, Armies in the Air, many Suns, as many Meteors, which must denote the fall of great Men, the death of Princes, desolations like those of <hi>Germany,</hi> the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volt and division of the people: and thus we must conceive, if, after all these wonders <hi>Pharaohs,</hi> heart be yet <hi>hardened,</hi> and will not let these Children of <hi>Israel</hi> go away with the <hi>spoil</hi> of the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> viz. <hi>Church-men</hi> and <hi>Cavaliers,</hi> he and his host must be swallowed up in a <hi>Red Sea</hi> of <hi>blood.</hi> The Devil hath got a Bishop already, and appeared in his shape to a Scholar at <hi>Oxford.</hi> If he appeared there, sure it was but once, who appears so often in this lying Pamphleter. The <hi>cause</hi> must needs be disowned by God, which needs the <hi>Father</hi> of <hi>lies</hi> to support it. The Devil which appeared in the shape of a <hi>Samuel,</hi> need not in theirs, who, outside Saints, may be more to his advantage, to keep inside Devils.</p>
            <p>A <hi>Cathedral</hi> appears in the air with some glim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mering kind of glory, but soon obscured by black
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:199216:5"/> clouds, and consum'd by Fire; while a little obscure Church of <hi>Presbytery</hi> appears glorious out of her ruines, and all this <hi>Verily, verily,</hi> and <hi>In good sooth,</hi> as certain as the fire from Heaven, mentioned by their <hi>Phanatick Brightman,</hi> destroyed the <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christ</hi> at <hi>Rome,</hi> in the year 1650. or their <hi>Sedge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wicks Dooms-dayes</hi> came.</p>
            <p>Farewel Church; now for the State.</p>
            <p>Blazing Comets, resembling Swords, and dart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Fire must be seen (by God knows only whom, and when, but as true as the rest, and the rest as <hi>Lucians</hi> true History,) impending over <hi>White-hall,</hi> Farewel King: over the Parliament Houses, Adieu Parliament. Thus Heaven and Earth can keep no truce with them, who could violate the <hi>gude Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tish Covenant,</hi> made for the preservation and honour of King and Parliament. The Children of <hi>Babylon</hi> require of them Songs. How can they sing in a strange Land, or a Land estranged by singing <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonish</hi> superstition? All who correspond notwith their whimzies are incurable <hi>Babylonians,</hi> must perish by the Sword, or these great Apostles will have Fire called dovvn from Heaven to destroy them.</p>
            <p>Next enters the old <hi>Presbyterian Prologue to War</hi> a Book intituled, A <hi>Petition for peace, with the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of the Liturgie.</hi> I must confess with <hi>Zan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chius, Non novi istam Reformatorum Theologiam,</hi> I understand not the Divinity of these Reformers, who pray (if I may use the Fathers words against Hereticks) <hi>Quasi multitudo verborum praevaleat apud Deum,</hi> as if multitude of words could onely prevail with God, and by all their <hi>canting quotations</hi> of Scripture, teach us only to remember that of our
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:199216:6"/> Saviour, to beware of those hypocrites which <hi>make long prayers,</hi> and use <hi>vain repetitions, as if they should be hear'd only by their much babling.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>model</hi> resembles a Countrey Taylors <hi>Cloak-bag;</hi> and as soon <hi>Christianity</hi> might be conveyed to the <hi>Turks</hi> in such a <hi>Cloak-bag</hi> made by the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>texture of a thousand <hi>lists,</hi> as Religion conveyed into the <hi>English</hi> by the uncouth Contexture of so many <hi>shreds</hi> of Scripture, made into a <hi>Liturgie</hi> by these <hi>Arch-Botchers</hi> of <hi>Reformation.</hi> Who soberly peruses them, will think them mad above the relief of <hi>Hellebore.</hi> The Priest in <hi>Acosta</hi> may seem equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly sober, who hearing a <hi>Gypsie</hi> cant in Scripture Phrase, phancyed himself born <hi>anew</hi> of that <hi>Mary,</hi> who could not conceive less then by the holy Ghost to bring forth a <hi>Messiah;</hi> who, by the advantage of an unhappy memory, <hi>tortured</hi> in as many places of Scripture for the proof of his Divinity, as these <hi>writhe</hi> into a <hi>Liturgy;</hi> or D. <hi>Causabons</hi> Countreyman, who related the joys of Heaven till he talked him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self into a <hi>Phrensey.</hi> She, who gathered up Oysters &amp; Cockle-shels, broken Glass, and every glittering gayety; and perswaded her self each was a present from an Emperour espoused to her, made rational discourses if compared with theirs, who by the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of an <hi>Ursins Cathechism, Calvins Institutions,</hi> a <hi>Wollebius, scraps</hi> of Fathers, glean'd from common place Books, or fragments of <hi>History</hi> from the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice byass'd <hi>Centuriators,</hi> a <hi>Geneva</hi> Bible, a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordance, a little dabling in <hi>Keckerman</hi> for division and sub-division, phancy themselves strange <hi>Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bies</hi> in Divinity; when they are onely shallow-<hi>Pud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dles,</hi> which seem to show Sun, Moon, Stars, all the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:199216:6"/> glories of Celestial bodies, and yet may be fathom'd with a little finger. But these <hi>shallow waters</hi> will be always making the greatest noyse, as they did at the late conference with the <hi>Praelatical Clergy,</hi> where they were exceeded in all things beside <hi>Clamor. St, Augustine</hi> foretold the effects of such <hi>Conferences,</hi> in <hi>Quid promovebis exercitatissime Scrp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turarum,</hi> &amp;c. If the most exercised in the <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures</hi> defend, it shall be denied; if denied, it shall be defended. A voice may be lost, but nothing gain'd beside the <hi>anger</hi> of <hi>Schismaticks.</hi> The pious Concessions of the <hi>Learned</hi> &amp; <hi>Reverend Fathers</hi> to gratifie these <hi>Babes</hi> in <hi>Divinity,</hi> weak ones in faith, cannot satisfie the strong in passions; as the last word at the conference, they must have the first in print, by a <hi>rare new Liturgie,</hi> lest the <hi>Bishop</hi> should put his foot in the pot before them who allow <hi>common Prayer,</hi> no name above <hi>pottage,</hi> though that they so call may resemble that <hi>pottage</hi> the <hi>Angel</hi> brought <hi>Daniel,</hi> while this of theirs can resemble none bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, then that which made the <hi>Prophet</hi> cry out, <hi>There is death in the Pot.</hi> Hence some fear this <hi>conference</hi> may produce effects, answering those of that unpolitick and dishonourable Colloquy at <hi>Hampton Court,</hi> whence we deriv'd that Deluge of miseries, which over-run <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State.</hi> Thence sprung that <hi>brain-sick generation,</hi> which afterwards pretended to be of Gods <hi>Privy Council;</hi> could di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinguish betwixt the <hi>Elect</hi> and <hi>Reprobate,</hi> an opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which lent a City of <hi>refuge</hi> to the <hi>Ignorant</hi> and a <hi>Sanctuary</hi> to the most <hi>impious,</hi> if they could attain to the <hi>kuack</hi> of <hi>dissimulation.</hi> Hence every Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>critical <hi>Sniveller,</hi> insignificant in the State before,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:199216:7"/> became considerable, while addle <hi>whimzies</hi> of over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heated <hi>brains</hi> were brought in competition with the till then unquestioned, and at least legal <hi>professi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of a <hi>Church.</hi> But (God be praised) we need not fear Sparrow-blasting, or danger from those, who, Sparrow-like, open from ear to ear, callow and unfledg'd, chirping upon every hedge, and leaving their own nests defiled. For though the disease is as Epidemical as ever, we are better provided with <hi>Antidotes.</hi> The Parliament Act is now to be put in execution, which provides that the <hi>Bag-pipers</hi> of <hi>sedition</hi> of little livings and less worths, must no more tune their Pipes in opposition to <hi>Authority,</hi> to make themselves the <hi>Darlings</hi> of the <hi>Rabble.</hi> No sanctifyed bellows made by the advantage of an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti-clergie Lecturers Lungs, can blow Fire about 3. Kingdoms, since the most <hi>Reverend</hi> and most <hi>pious Prelates</hi> will provide <hi>grave</hi> and <hi>sober Divines</hi> to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spense the milk of the <hi>Word,</hi> to cure the <hi>Wild fire</hi> which kindled all our <hi>combustions</hi> in <hi>state;</hi> and by their own frequent visiting of their Sees, provide against those inundations of Irreligion, Prophanenes, and Hypocrisy, which might over-run the fences of the <hi>Church.</hi> Thus the Episcopal Clergie shall sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice more to <hi>Minerva</hi> then <hi>Bacchus,</hi> the Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>episcopal shall no more sacrifice to his belly, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide himself and family <hi>feasts</hi> out of the <hi>fasts</hi> of the Brethren, or <hi>ruines</hi> of our Church. Could this fail, we cannot believe his Majesty by being over graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, should take away all grace from his Subjects: give them his <hi>Crown</hi> in his <hi>Prerogatives,</hi> his <hi>Sword</hi> in his <hi>Militia,</hi> or <hi>Scepter</hi> in a <hi>negative Voyce,</hi> and lend them occasion, if not in desire, yet in effect to be
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:199216:7"/>
               <hi>Regicides,</hi> intrust the <hi>baffled Presbyter</hi> to be chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by his more politique <hi>younger Brother</hi> of <hi>Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendency,</hi> and the <hi>Independent</hi> in dividing the spoil one to destroy the other. It is ill trusting of Goods in Thieves hands, in hopes they may fall out. If all is not granted, nothing is granted. Now, now is the time: the <hi>cup</hi> of <hi>abomination</hi> is full, and the <hi>Saints</hi> would be pouring it out upon the Earth, by a <hi>snotty plot.</hi> All <hi>Sects</hi> must again twist into an <hi>association,</hi> make a rope of sand, must do miracles. <hi>Herod</hi> and <hi>Pilate</hi> must be made <hi>friends,</hi> the <hi>Presbyter</hi> who <hi>revil'd,</hi> and the <hi>Independent</hi> who <hi>crucified,</hi> that both may be against <hi>Christ. Presbyter</hi> and <hi>Independent</hi> make up the Antichrist, while they pretend to be against him, as if the only way to be <hi>for Christ,</hi> was to be <hi>against</hi> the <hi>Christ</hi> of <hi>the Lord,</hi> our <hi>anointed So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign,</hi> and his <hi>Prophets</hi> the <hi>Holy Bishops.</hi> There are many here imprisoned; whether the statute a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst <hi>Gypsies</hi> lays hold on <hi>them,</hi> or <hi>they</hi> are <hi>commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> for <hi>Witch-craft,</hi> is incertain. Some say they have been alwayes <hi>canting vagrants</hi> in <hi>opinion;</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers that they are guilty of <hi>Rebellion,</hi> which is the sin of <hi>Witch-craft;</hi> and we may suspect theirs a sin not unlike to this, which is so incapable of <hi>repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance:</hi> else they could admit nothing so <hi>opposite</hi> to <hi>gratitude,</hi> and <hi>allegiance to his</hi> Majesty, to the late <hi>Act of Oblivion,</hi> to <hi>neighbourly love,</hi> to the <hi>discreet care</hi> of <hi>themselves,</hi> as to embroyl <hi>themselves</hi> in what they are inconcern'd, and so render them <hi>Traytors</hi> to the <hi>King, Vipers</hi> to their <hi>native Country, forfeit</hi> their <hi>right, disoblige</hi> his <hi>Majesty hazard</hi> their <hi>own happiness,</hi> and <hi>instruct</hi> the <hi>world</hi> who were the <hi>contrivers</hi> and <hi>fomenters</hi> of <hi>all</hi> our <hi>ruines,</hi> by a
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:199216:8"/>
               <hi>Covenant</hi> which <hi>obliges</hi> to nothing beside <hi>Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No <hi>Ceremony,</hi> no <hi>Bishop;</hi> No <hi>Bishop</hi> no <hi>King. Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty</hi> is the <hi>superstition,</hi> and St. <hi>Hier.</hi> Remedy against <hi>Schism,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Hier.</hi> ad <hi>Evag.</hi> in Schismatis remedium factum est quod postea unus electus, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Nisi exors quaedam &amp; ab om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus eminens potestas Episcopo daretur, tot effent schismata quot sacerdotes.</p>
               </note>
               <hi>Episcopacy,</hi> is the <hi>Disease</hi> which troubles them, who could willingly <hi>admit</hi> as many <hi>Schisms</hi> as <hi>Priests,</hi> by denying a <hi>pre-eminence</hi> to the <hi>Bishop</hi> And since as S. <hi>Ambrose,</hi> Haeresies cannot arise,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>St. Amb.</hi> Non aliunde Hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reses exortae, aut nata Schis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mata, quam ind<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, quod sacer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dotes non venerantur.</note> but by rendring the <hi>Priest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood</hi> contemptible, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept their own <hi>Linsey Wolsey upstarts e face popelli, out of the dreggs of the people,</hi> like the <hi>Priests</hi> of the <hi>seditious Iews</hi> in <hi>Iose<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phus</hi> all they cannot make so, they would render so by <hi>scandal.</hi> All who <hi>disdain</hi> the <hi>phaneies</hi> of the <hi>loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ser times,</hi> and walk not <hi>ungirt</hi> that they may be no longer <hi>unblest,</hi> are intitl'd <hi>men of the cir-cingle.</hi> A <hi>lean Priest</hi> is resembled to a <hi>walking staff</hi> bound a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout with a <hi>black Ribbon;</hi> his <hi>look</hi> must <hi>prophecy</hi> a <hi>dearth</hi> of the <hi>food of life in the Land</hi> or his <hi>Quadra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gesimal face</hi> must foreshow a <hi>strict Lent,</hi> and call to remembrance the <hi>fasts</hi> of the <hi>Church.</hi> A <hi>fat Clergie man</hi> must be one of plump <hi>Bacchus</hi> his <hi>Priests,</hi> and even the Boyes will upbraid him of <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>providence</hi> for trusting so great a <hi>Tun</hi> to the mercy of one <hi>hoop,</hi> viz. A <hi>Canonical belt.</hi> At the sight of a <hi>Red fac'd Person,</hi> they cry out of the <hi>brick</hi> which must build up <hi>Babylon,</hi> declaim against <hi>Antichrist</hi> in his nose; the <hi>Roman Rubrick,</hi> or our <hi>Church Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lendar</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:199216:8"/> must be seen in his <hi>Holy-day face:</hi> It would be well if <hi>Symony</hi> ally'd none to <hi>Antichrist</hi> (which the imcomparable Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi> will have to be <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> &amp; happy for this <hi>Nation,</hi> if those (who are falsly aspersed with <hi>superstition</hi>) be not found <hi>real Idolaters;</hi> so St. <hi>Paul</hi> calls <hi>covetous Persons.</hi> Here is a great noise about <hi>Pluralities</hi> and <hi>Non-residence,</hi> amongst the <hi>Non-comformists;</hi> but I fear a more <hi>just complaint</hi> among the <hi>poor Cavaliers,</hi> who have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended BLOOD and FORTUNES in the <hi>Cause</hi> of <hi>Religion,</hi> and yet amidst the <hi>Glories</hi> of the <hi>Clergie,</hi> by their want of <hi>Charity,</hi> can find some not onely making all <hi>Religion vain</hi> towards them, but even a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst themselves, while a <hi>Curate</hi> of no less <hi>parts,</hi> and perhaps more <hi>sufferings</hi> &amp; <hi>loyalty</hi> truckles un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and does <hi>Hackney</hi> work in <hi>Divinity</hi> for an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>considerable salary, to one who ows a <hi>Mandamus</hi> to <hi>bribes,</hi> or <hi>pretences,</hi> &amp;c. Such a Dr. as <hi>King Iames</hi> upon the like case menaced with the shaving off of his <hi>great Beard,</hi> and sending again to <hi>School</hi> in his <hi>long Coat,</hi> who an <hi>Old man</hi> in <hi>years</hi> was but a <hi>Baby</hi> in <hi>Divinity,</hi> vy'd with his poor <hi>Curate.</hi> Thus our Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious <hi>Prince</hi> in these HAPPIER REVOLUTI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ONS hath more cause then his less pious Predeces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sor <hi>Henry the Eight</hi> had to complain of <hi>old Mump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>simus</hi> and <hi>new Sumpfimus</hi> to a <hi>Parliament.</hi> Few re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>semble old <hi>Bishop Fisher,</hi> who would rather em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace <hi>poverty</hi> with a poor old wife at <hi>Rochester,</hi> then by an <hi>Exchange,</hi> gain a more <hi>plentiful dowry.</hi> Yet, our scarce to be <hi>parallel'd Thorndike,</hi> by a <hi>Sanhedrim</hi> of <hi>Iews,</hi> a whole <hi>Assembly of Divines,</hi> contents him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self with a <hi>Prebends</hi> place: And I lately heard the pious Dr. <hi>Thriscross</hi> praise God for the <hi>attaining,</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:199216:9"/> what he called far <hi>above his deserts,</hi> A <hi>stipend</hi> of <hi>fifty pound per annum</hi> at the <hi>Charter-house.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the case of the <hi>Clergie</hi> and <hi>Cavaltry,</hi> reduced to <hi>beggary</hi> by <hi>Loyalty,</hi> we cannot expect less then the fashions of <hi>Beggars, howling noise, sores,</hi> and <hi>sufferings;</hi> the least <hi>necessity</hi> attended on by the greatest <hi>pretences, Impudence</hi> and <hi>Ignorance,</hi> the old <hi>pass-ports</hi> for <hi>preferment</hi> seldom miss, like some <hi>rapacious</hi> and <hi>counterfeit Beggars</hi> in the dealing of the <hi>dole</hi> of <hi>state</hi> a treble share, while <hi>unserved vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue</hi> silently bewails the <hi>real want</hi> of <hi>merit</hi> in others; and perhaps her own nor less <hi>real necessitie</hi> If the <hi>streams</hi> issuing from the <hi>Fountain</hi> of all <hi>Honor</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to fructifie <hi>Loyalty,</hi> be <hi>perverted,</hi> to <hi>water</hi> the <hi>plants</hi> of <hi>rebellion,</hi> the <hi>fault</hi> is not in the <hi>Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain,</hi> but in the <hi>perverter.</hi> If <hi>exhalation</hi> are raised which produce <hi>Comets</hi> and <hi>Meteor,</hi> portentuous to <hi>Kingdoms,</hi> or they descend in <hi>Thunder, Storms</hi> and <hi>Lightning,</hi> which render a <hi>Land Barren,</hi> instead of those <hi>benigner showrs,</hi> which make all things <hi>fertile;</hi> the fault is not in the <hi>Sun,</hi> but in the <hi>corruption</hi> of our <hi>prutred climate.</hi> Our ROYAL SUN doth good to all, <hi>Good and Bad, Friend and Enemy,</hi> shines upon <hi>Dunghills</hi> as well as <hi>Gardens.</hi> It can be no wonder, if a <hi>stench</hi> be returned for <hi>beams,</hi> as well as those <hi>Odours</hi> of <hi>virtue,</hi> which may <hi>perfume</hi> the <hi>higher Region</hi> of the <hi>Court.</hi> All things are not pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to his <hi>beams.</hi> Though the <hi>Sun</hi> is intituled to an <hi>all-seeing-eye,</hi> to gratify <hi>our phancies;</hi> we cannot believe all affairs <hi>unobscur'd</hi> to Majesty. <hi>Kings</hi> may be therefore allowed the liberty of <hi>Looking-Glasses,</hi> and even <hi>those</hi> of the <hi>Muses</hi> at the sight of which no one is affrighted, except he resembles
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:199216:9"/> the <hi>deformed fellow</hi> in that of <hi>Tom Randolph,</hi> at the uglines of his own shape. The aspiring <hi>Minion</hi> may be seen in <hi>A Sejanus; Conspirators</hi> in <hi>A Cataline, Every man in his Humor, and every man out of his Humor,</hi> is Personated in <hi>Iohnsons</hi> Works; even from the perfumed <hi>Court Gull</hi> to the <hi>City Widgin. The zeal of the Land,</hi> brought in for a <hi>Puppet</hi> to adorn <hi>Bartholomew Fair,</hi> may show the <hi>Whimzies</hi> of ours. <hi>Tribulation &amp; Ananias</hi> in the <hi>Alchymist</hi> these <hi>Saints,</hi> who had got a <hi>stone</hi> in their <hi>noddles,</hi> which might renew a <hi>Golden Age,</hi> and introduce the <hi>fifth Monarchy</hi> for the <hi>Rule</hi> of such <hi>Utopian Zealots.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here are great accusations against <hi>Players.</hi> The old Spirit of <hi>Histriomastix</hi> is conjur'd up, to be <hi>troublesom</hi> and <hi>petulant</hi> against these fellows, who (as some affirm) can represent nothing so <hi>vile,</hi> as what they really are in their own persons. If so, it would not be amiss, while <hi>playes</hi> are used as Mr. <hi>Busbie</hi> used <hi>Martial</hi> (who <hi>gelt</hi> him for his <hi>Obscenity</hi>) that <hi>Actors</hi> may be <hi>castrated,</hi> to take away the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casions of <hi>Scandal.</hi> If this <hi>Turkish</hi> mode could not preserve the <hi>chastity</hi> at the one, it might rarely <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage</hi> the voyces ar the other <hi>Theatre,</hi> where some say they are kept bare; sure they must ow it to their <hi>Ingenuity,</hi> which bestows no greater <hi>badge</hi> then that of <hi>beggary</hi> on her <hi>Servants.</hi> None can deny them the most <hi>lively Representations,</hi> Else the <hi>Siedge of Rhodes</hi> so frequently seen before our <hi>City Gates,</hi> could not perswade some it must be as long in <hi>acting</hi> here, as before that <hi>City.</hi> Their Neighbours Lord it like those of the <hi>other House,</hi> those former <hi>Pig-wig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins</hi> of <hi>State:</hi> But with the <hi>Cat</hi> in the <hi>Fable discover</hi> themselves still in their beloved <hi>Beggars Bush,</hi> or
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:199216:10"/>
               <hi>Iovial Crew,</hi> and have the advantage only of <hi>Will and the Wits with Scenes,</hi> that they can be bold with an <hi>Alchymist</hi> of <hi>Bens,</hi> who can give a <hi>reputation</hi> to the worst of <hi>mettals,</hi> while the worst of his works can excell the whole <hi>Opera of</hi> others. These are the the <hi>quibbles</hi> of some <hi>Dablers</hi> in <hi>wit</hi> or <hi>slight Fresh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> in <hi>Poesy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Ladies</hi> (those she <hi>Critiques,</hi> who by relation of <hi>Sex</hi> pretend affinity to the <hi>Muses</hi>) will have their concerns, though their <hi>judgements,</hi> like their <hi>beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,</hi> is but <hi>skin deep,</hi> and as many <hi>patches</hi> may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired to make up the <hi>defects</hi> of the one, as the <hi>ruins</hi> of the other: inconcern'd in the Players <hi>Girls patches</hi> (which the <hi>Zealots</hi> call <hi>Lusts Idols,</hi> the <hi>spot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Calves</hi> of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> set up in such <hi>Idolatrous houses</hi> to be worshipped) can be troubled to see a <hi>Lady</hi> translated into a <hi>Beggar,</hi> and that <hi>Ioan</hi> which used to be as good as my <hi>Lady,</hi> in the dark only, a <hi>Lady</hi> now must represent before the eyes of all peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, to the <hi>disgrace</hi> of <hi>Mercenary honour,</hi> which cost their Husbands so dear to Courtiers, to <hi>gratify</hi> their <hi>idler humours.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>City zeal</hi> flyes high, and taking an <hi>Arise</hi> from the <hi>Pulpit,</hi> will allow <hi>Theaters</hi> only <hi>Nests</hi> of <hi>Prophaneness,</hi> and <hi>a brand</hi> of <hi>Levity</hi> must be affix'd to the <hi>Visitants.</hi>
               <q>Men of the same profession are sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom friends.</q> The <hi>pulpit</hi> &amp; <hi>Stage</hi> are in competition. The <hi>Pulpit</hi> pleads <hi>Custome,</hi> two or three <hi>Apprenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ships</hi> served, the <hi>Votes</hi> of <hi>two Houses,</hi> and what is most obsetvable, <hi>Bishops</hi> and <hi>Stage Playes</hi> were vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted down on the same day, that the <hi>Mime</hi> and <hi>Satyre</hi> might be both confined thither; The <hi>Church</hi> having no <hi>grave Fathers</hi> to <hi>reprehend,</hi> and the <hi>Muses</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:199216:10"/> wanting a <hi>Looking Glass</hi> to <hi>represent</hi> their <hi>Vice,</hi> made a whole Land the <hi>Stages</hi> of <hi>Rapine</hi> and <hi>Blood;</hi> The <hi>Tragedies</hi> which came from the <hi>Pulpit</hi> carrying alwayes the most danger. They have spoak their <hi>Prologues,</hi> but we need not fear the silencing of them before they re-act their bloody <hi>Scenes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Good Iosias,</hi> nor <hi>Good Hezekiah</hi> ever went to see <hi>Stage Playes;</hi> belch'd out one of the <hi>Shimeis,</hi> who will not leave <hi>rayling,</hi> not <hi>throwing stones</hi> against <hi>David;</hi> but let them take heed lest the <hi>Inquisition for blood</hi> find them out, and they <hi>descend not into their Graves with peace,</hi> as the little and contemptible Person <hi>Iohn Iames</hi> (as the <hi>Saints</hi> will have it, <hi>Another Zachaeus</hi>) hath climb'd up a <hi>Tree</hi> to see <hi>Christ.</hi> And God grant none of these <hi>Ambitious Pablers,</hi> or <hi>Bable</hi>-builders, may so <hi>climb,</hi> &amp; instead of <hi>seeing a Savior,</hi> or <hi>reaching of heaven break their necks</hi> &amp; <hi>fall down</hi> into a Pit of <hi>Eternal destruction,</hi> &amp; make some neither <hi>dis-ingenious,</hi> nor <hi>dis-loyal,</hi> accuse <hi>Laws</hi> made <hi>ad terrorem Populi,</hi> of <hi>harshness,</hi> while they take hold on such <hi>Ideots</hi> and <hi>Lunaticks</hi> as may be allow'd <hi>favourable constructions</hi> in the most <hi>enor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous transgressions</hi> of the <hi>Law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Presbyter</hi> in his own <hi>defence</hi> can scarce pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce a <hi>Council</hi> or <hi>Father;</hi> yet against <hi>stage Playes</hi> may <hi>muster</hi> up an <hi>Army</hi> to fight against this <hi>Bell and the Dragon</hi> set up in <hi>High places.</hi> But the good minded man, <hi>Histriomastix,</hi> may onely swell him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self in a <hi>volume,</hi> to instruct the World, onely he is <hi>mistaken,</hi> as the rest of his brethren, whose <hi>valour</hi> onely proceeds of their <hi>Ignorance,</hi> who <hi>(More Anda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitarum pugnant)</hi> fight alwayes blind-fold. <hi>Logo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>machies, Sciamachies, Homonyma's</hi> and <hi>Circulations</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:199216:11"/> are befitting such <hi>Champions,</hi> who have nothing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>side the <hi>Chymara's</hi> of their own <hi>vertiginous noddles</hi> to <hi>combate</hi> with. St. <hi>Cyprian, Isidore, Haymo, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selm▪</hi> &amp;c. might couple <hi>Players</hi> and <hi>Whores, Play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houses</hi> and <hi>Brothers,</hi> as <hi>Tacitus</hi> rankes <hi>stews</hi> and <hi>Theaters. Prosper</hi> truely name them <hi>Mimical un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanesses, Damascen</hi> and <hi>Eusebius</hi> call them <hi>Schools of Lusts.</hi> But sure we have no <hi>Heliogabulus,</hi> who will have <hi>Whores</hi> introduced, not to <hi>Personate</hi> but <hi>really do</hi> the <hi>act of sin</hi> upon the <hi>Stage.</hi> No <hi>Roman Theatre</hi> styled by <hi>Tertullian</hi> the <hi>Temple of Venus,</hi> where <hi>Whoredoms</hi> were priviledged, and <hi>Adulteries</hi> not numbred among <hi>Vices.</hi> No <hi>Grecian Actors</hi> to introduce <hi>swimming Whores</hi> in <hi>Cisterns,</hi> with <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stures,</hi> more <hi>sinfull</hi> then those of <hi>Lust-provoking Are<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines</hi> Pictures. We have no <hi>Tragedies</hi> dedicated to <hi>Bacchus,</hi> not <hi>Comedies</hi> to <hi>Priapus. Drunkenness</hi> and <hi>Lust</hi> are not the only <hi>Ingredients</hi> in <hi>Playes,</hi> where in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stead of <hi>representing</hi> the <hi>follies</hi> of <hi>others,</hi> they <hi>Acted</hi> their <hi>ownshames.</hi> If <hi>Vice</hi> is introduced, she is at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended by <hi>Punishment.</hi> Who could love a <hi>dirt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>smear'd Whore</hi> made <hi>black</hi> as her <hi>own guilt,</hi> or be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amor'd of her <hi>naked exposure,</hi> when it is only for the <hi>Beadles Whip? Pillory'd Ears</hi> never rendered <hi>Cheating Amiable,</hi> nor a <hi>turn</hi> at <hi>Tyburn,</hi> ever made <hi>Villany</hi> counted <hi>precious.</hi> He who <hi>flyes</hi> a <hi>Sermon,</hi> may be <hi>over-taken</hi> at a <hi>Play,</hi> while a <hi>delight</hi> may be translated into a <hi>Sacrifice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No <hi>Sempronius Sophus</hi> need give a <hi>Bill of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vorce</hi> to his Wife, for visiting <hi>Stage Playes,</hi> nor do we want the <hi>Constitutions of Iustinian</hi> to make it <hi>Lawfull.</hi> St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> need not fear <hi>Virgins</hi> made <hi>Mothers</hi> without <hi>Husbands</hi> &amp;c. The <hi>Fathers</hi> might
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:199216:11"/> write Books of <hi>Retractations;</hi> And St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self might cry out, as some did of him, <hi>Lactantius, Victorinus,</hi> and <hi>Hilarius, Quanto auro &amp; argento &amp; veste exiit ex Aegypto?</hi> While the <hi>Wine</hi> or <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils Poesy</hi> becomes the <hi>scourge</hi> of them in their <hi>Members,</hi> lashing them out of their <hi>follies,</hi> inrich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Christianity</hi> with the <hi>Ornaments</hi> of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> which St. <hi>Austin</hi> applyes to <hi>Arts</hi> and <hi>Sciences; Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Inventions,</hi> but taken from <hi>them,</hi> as <hi>Aegyptian spoyls,</hi> and translated to the use of the <hi>Church.</hi> The <hi>Rich Gluttons care</hi> for his <hi>Bretheren,</hi> may not now seem <hi>fruitless,</hi> while the <hi>Grave</hi> makes her returns upon the <hi>Stage,</hi> which his <hi>Alliance</hi> in <hi>Bestiality</hi> may hear, could they neglect <hi>Moses and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets.</hi> Could <hi>Cato</hi> survive, he would not only <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to go out,</hi> but <hi>sit and be delighted;</hi> where he might hear more <hi>Wisdom</hi> then he was <hi>intituled to.</hi> The greatest <hi>Philosophers</hi> might rejoyce to find here their <hi>Long dreamed on Elixir,</hi> while <hi>Ben</hi> the onely <hi>true Alchymist Converts</hi> all <hi>Metalls</hi> into <hi>Gold</hi> by the advantage of the <hi>Laboratory,</hi> of whose <hi>brain</hi> the <hi>Wisdom</hi> of <hi>Greece and Rome</hi> the <hi>Riches</hi> of <hi>all Ages</hi> became tributary to ours, and inriched the <hi>English Tongue. Playes</hi> of less value then his, have <hi>furnished</hi> out a <hi>Statesman:</hi> his very <hi>scraps gleaned</hi> up by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, have made a competent <hi>stock</hi> of <hi>wit</hi> to drive a <hi>Trade</hi> in <hi>Poetry,</hi> and taught the <hi>Courtly Thing</hi> without the addition of prophaner <hi>Damme's dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course</hi> enough, to make a <hi>Complement.</hi> Had he not been an <hi>Age</hi> from being <hi>understood,</hi> one <hi>Play</hi> of his, might have laught more into <hi>Wit</hi> and <hi>Virtue,</hi> then twenty tedious <hi>Lectures,</hi> (as it was not long ago) who to the eternal dishonour of the <hi>Pulpit,</hi> took
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:199216:12"/> more vains in a <hi>single one,</hi> then most in twenty <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons.</hi> Impertinent and unnecessary <hi>School Questi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> (which King <hi>Iames</hi> complained of to the <hi>Arch-Bishop</hi>) with some insignificant <hi>scraps</hi> of <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Latine tortured</hi> in, tormented some <hi>Pulpits. Invectives</hi> against <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State, Whimzies</hi> about <hi>Antichrist,</hi> the accomplishment of <hi>Bright mans Melancholly Dreams,</hi> and such <hi>stuff</hi> as was to be studyed only in <hi>Bethelem Colledge;</hi> laid siege to others, while <hi>mouth Granado's</hi> were ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to raise <hi>Combustions</hi> in three <hi>Kingdoms.</hi> Neither were the <hi>unpolitick</hi> and <hi>dis-ingenious</hi> discourses of <hi>Religion</hi> better managed (except in the incompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Bishop <hi>Laud,</hi> the <hi>Reverend Hooker, Chillings<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth,</hi> and some few; as since in the most excellent Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi> Dr. <hi>Sanderson Thorndike, &amp;c.</hi>) These <hi>loose</hi> and <hi>loop hol'd Phancies,</hi> onely served to <hi>multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply Words,</hi> and the <hi>Itch of dispute</hi> proved only instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental to produce (what the Ingenious Sir <hi>Henry Wooton</hi> would have inscribed on his <hi>Tomb) The Scab of the Church;</hi> and thence gave occasion to the <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stemperature,</hi> which so many years hath discompo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed the <hi>State.</hi> It hath been the unhappy fault of some <hi>Priests,</hi> most <hi>Actors,</hi> and not a few <hi>Poets,</hi> by <hi>evil lives</hi> to have scandalized the <hi>best of Doctrines.</hi> The <hi>Troubles</hi> which poor <hi>Ben</hi> indured for his <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours</hi> to reclaim <hi>Ignorance</hi> and <hi>Atheism</hi> in <hi>Court, City, Countrey,</hi> might have intituled him to a <hi>State Martyr,</hi> could he have been guilty of so much <hi>Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crisy,</hi> as might have made him capable of the name of a <hi>Saint.</hi> No man can misdoubt him, what every <hi>Poet</hi> calls himself, a <hi>Prophet,</hi> since a fatal experience hath found verified the discoveries in <hi>Iohnsons Plays</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:199216:12"/> have proved of greater <hi>Truth</hi> and more <hi>Consequence,</hi> then the <hi>Phanatique Notes,</hi> licensed to the <hi>dispara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> and <hi>ruin</hi> of a <hi>Church,</hi> affixed to <hi>Evangelical Revelations.</hi> It is great pitty he should <hi>hear ill</hi> of all, who taught all, who were capable, to <hi>speak</hi> so <hi>well.</hi> This makes me inlarge of him, who, <hi>Homer like,</hi> comprehends all <hi>Poets,</hi> and though some intitle him a <hi>drunken one,</hi> no <hi>vomit</hi> could be so bad as might not be <hi>lick'd</hi> up — and, even at a third hand, seem excellent to those <hi>Ideots,</hi> who have <hi>Ignorance</hi> and <hi>Impudence</hi> enough to dispise his <hi>works.</hi> If there be any <hi>Play</hi> made up of a <hi>Cupid</hi> and a <hi>Fidle,</hi> or such as our <hi>French Comedians</hi> Act, the <hi>Machines</hi> of <hi>Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na</hi> and <hi>Endimion,</hi> or <hi>Orpheus</hi> descending into <hi>Hell,</hi> according to the description of the pious and chast <hi>Ovid,</hi> in his eleventh Book of his <hi>Metamorphosis,</hi> let them fall into the hand of the <hi>Executioner,</hi> the zealous <hi>Histriomastrix.</hi> I could wish every <hi>Roscius</hi> a <hi>Cicero; Poesy</hi> will never want a Sir <hi>Philip Sidney,</hi> and <hi>Ben. Iohnson</hi> will be precious to <hi>Ages,</hi> while <hi>Histriomastix</hi> (like the <hi>Flatterers</hi> in <hi>Adrians</hi> time, <hi>fume punitur fumos vendens</hi>) who vents smoak is punished with it, and serves only to light <hi>To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bacco.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Use</hi> of <hi>Playes</hi> is <hi>lawfull,</hi> but the <hi>Abuse,</hi> like the <hi>Corruptions</hi> of <hi>best things,</hi> proves of worst <hi>Conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence.</hi> I could wish every <hi>Gentleman</hi> would learn his <hi>Calling,</hi> by a <hi>Treatise</hi> so intituled, and written by the sober and learned Pen of an excellent <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late.</hi> He who affects <hi>Musick</hi> may hear it employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in a <hi>Diviner Service,</hi> and need not expend his <hi>Money</hi> for the loss of <hi>Time.</hi> If this take not, may the <hi>Elder Brother</hi> (like him in <hi>Fletcher</hi>) traverse
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:199216:13"/> the <hi>Stories</hi> of the <hi>Ancient Heroes,</hi> read over the <hi>Lives</hi> of the <hi>Great</hi> &amp; <hi>Good-men, distil</hi> the <hi>sweetness</hi> from the <hi>Poets spring,</hi> and <hi>digest</hi> all into <hi>manners;</hi> and not, like his <hi>Spruce Courtier, know</hi> no use of the <hi>Moon,</hi> beside the lighting him from <hi>Taverns, Playes</hi> and <hi>Brothels;</hi> or the <hi>benefit</hi> of the <hi>Sun,</hi> except to wear <hi>slashed Doublets.</hi> May no <hi>Fools</hi> be ready to <hi>Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice</hi> on the <hi>Altar</hi> of <hi>Fortune</hi> in a <hi>Shop</hi> of <hi>deceit;</hi> A <hi>Gaming House.</hi> No <hi>Knights</hi> mis-employ their <hi>Swords</hi> (as some report) in that dishonorable piece of Knight <hi>Errantry,</hi> to relieve the distressed <hi>Ladies</hi> of the <hi>Stews,</hi> nor suppose the <hi>Emblem</hi> of <hi>Chevalry</hi> is only to be made use of like a <hi>Scotch Spur,</hi> while <hi>Noble Families</hi> are swallowed up in <hi>Solomons deep Pit</hi> (so he calls a <hi>Whore) Rottenness siezing upon Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, Estates</hi> and <hi>Names</hi> for ever. If the printed <hi>Catalogue</hi> of <hi>Whores, Bawds, Pimps,</hi> scandalize not our <hi>City, Rome</hi> and <hi>Naples,</hi> nay, all <hi>Italy</hi> and <hi>Spain</hi> cannot outvie us for <hi>Brothels.</hi> His pious <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty</hi> spoil'd their <hi>Mart</hi> at St. <hi>Iameses,</hi> where <hi>meaz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led</hi> Swines flesh, and the flesh of such <hi>Asses</hi> was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed to sale, as from <hi>an Itch</hi> might produce a <hi>Neo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>politan Scab,</hi> to indanger a whole <hi>Nation.</hi> Neither could such <hi>Nests</hi> of <hi>Vermine</hi> be tolerated (against his Command) to <hi>fructify</hi> only for the <hi>Gallows,</hi> if negligent and corrupt Officers did not put in for half sharers with them, in the <hi>hire</hi> of <hi>Iniquity.</hi> I heard his late Majesty tell an Officer, the Old Earl of <hi>Nottingham,</hi> when he hear'd a Servant swear, swore two or three great Oaths, that if he did so again, he should be <hi>lay'd</hi> by the <hi>Heels:</hi> and how a swearing Earl intreated his Royal Father; every
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:199216:13"/> Prophaner of Gods Name might have his Tongue bored through with in hot Iron. Thus this Most Excellent Prince intimated how his Officers, instead of <hi>reforming</hi> others, <hi>instructed Sin</hi> by their <hi>Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples,</hi> and most like the <hi>Earl,</hi> who threw <hi>Squibs, Crackers,</hi> and <hi>Wildfire</hi> in his <hi>Oathes,</hi> and broke wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ser heads then his own at <hi>Masks,</hi> would be numbred among the <hi>Saints;</hi> yet to the <hi>dishonour</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> his <hi>Royal Master,</hi> and <hi>Himself,</hi> could gratifie the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil</hi> with such <hi>mouth Granado's,</hi> as might indanger <hi>Church and State.</hi> Our ROYAL MARTYR, (whose pious foot-steps our <hi>Gracious Soveraign</hi> fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows) in a Proclamation before our Army at <hi>Don<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caster</hi> used these (or not unlike) words? <hi>If any one cannot leave his Drunkenness, his Swearing and Prophanness, we command him to depart our Army, being confident God will bless us with a fewer, if a more Religious number. Thus,</hi> could either example or precept have prevail'd, the <hi>best</hi> of <hi>Princes</hi> (like him whose foot-steps he followed in the <hi>Red way</hi> of the <hi>Cross</hi>) should not have been scandaliz'd by our <hi>Pharisees,</hi> for conversing with <hi>Publicans</hi> and <hi>Sinners;</hi> nor could the <hi>People</hi> have been raised up by them against their <hi>King;</hi> to cry, <hi>Crucify him, Crucify him:</hi> The greatest <hi>Victime</hi> which suffered in so <hi>unworthy a way</hi> since our <hi>Saviour, for</hi> the <hi>Sins</hi> of a <hi>Prophane,</hi> and <hi>by</hi> the <hi>Sins</hi> of an <hi>Hypocritical Generation. Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneness</hi> and <hi>Hypocrisy</hi> have been the <hi>twin Devils</hi> who have troubled <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State;</hi> but the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil</hi> when he appears in the shape of an <hi>Angel of Light,</hi> alwayes carryes the most danger; Thus <hi>Lucifer</hi> can draw the <hi>Stars</hi> into a <hi>Conspiracy</hi> against
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:199216:14"/>
               <hi>God himself,</hi> and what he could not arrive to in <hi>Heaven</hi> can attain to in <hi>Earth</hi> by dethroning Gods <hi>Vicegerents.</hi> But though the <hi>Diseases</hi> seem as <hi>dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous</hi> as ever, and there may be some <hi>new,</hi> we need not be <hi>discouraged,</hi> while the <hi>Head</hi> and <hi>Body</hi> afford mutual <hi>Assistance</hi> to Master, with Gods blessing (as his Majesty hints) all <hi>difficulties.</hi> The good <hi>Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitians</hi> of the <hi>House of Commons</hi> at the first <hi>Consul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation</hi> strook at the <hi>Root, enervated</hi> all the <hi>Kings</hi> and their <hi>own Enemies,</hi> while they <hi>supplyed</hi> him with the <hi>Sinews of War,</hi> which may give <hi>security</hi> at home, and reputation abroad. They who adorn their <hi>Princes</hi> with <hi>Crowns</hi> and <hi>Scepters of Gold,</hi> and deny them it in their <hi>Revenue, Crown</hi> them only for <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice,</hi> resemble those who put a <hi>Crown</hi> and <hi>Purple</hi> on our <hi>Saviour;</hi> cry, <hi>hail King,</hi> and intend to <hi>Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cify,</hi> and can never want <hi>means.</hi> A <hi>Court</hi> will supply a <hi>Iudas;</hi> who, having bought a place, rather then want something to <hi>sell,</hi> will <hi>sell</hi> his <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Weak-sighted <hi>Parliaments</hi> by <hi>unseasonable prying</hi> into <hi>Sun-beams,</hi> the <hi>Princes Actions,</hi> have made them selves <hi>blind</hi> and <hi>giddy:</hi> but here are no <hi>prejudiced Phancies</hi> to <hi>mispresent Objects,</hi> no <hi>Icterick</hi> or <hi>blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shot Eyes,</hi> which apprehend nothing beside <hi>their own Colours;</hi> no one so ignorant as to ascribe <hi>twinckling</hi> to the <hi>Stars,</hi> when the <hi>defect</hi> is in his own <hi>weak sight.</hi> And though as in all <hi>Bodies,</hi> some <hi>Members</hi> are more honourable then <hi>others,</hi> and some cannot be named without <hi>scandal</hi> in any body, yet (to use his Majesties Words) the <hi>Lords Spiritual</hi> and <hi>Temporal</hi> and <hi>Commons</hi> of <hi>England</hi> met together to consult
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:199216:14"/> for the <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Safety</hi> of <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State,</hi> by which <hi>Parliaments</hi> are restored to their <hi>Lustre</hi> and <hi>Integrity</hi>) we cannot doubt any <hi>Member</hi> may be <hi>useless</hi> by not holding a <hi>Correspondence</hi> with the <hi>Head,</hi> or not <hi>Contributing</hi> to the good of the <hi>Body,</hi> by which only he may hope for <hi>preservation.</hi> Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience verifying his Gracious <hi>Speech, Who loves not the Head, cannot love the Body politick: and who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever doth not reverence this Parliament, can have lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle love for his Majesty.</hi> Here is no danger of <hi>dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring</hi> by <hi>partial Votes;</hi> rendring <hi>useless</hi> by <hi>sedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Tumults. Reason</hi> will not be <hi>condemned</hi> for an <hi>evil Councellor,</hi> or a <hi>Loyal Conscience,</hi> called a <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant Disease in the Heart,</hi> till <hi>desperation</hi> or <hi>want of opportunity</hi> to <hi>depart,</hi> or <hi>fear of certain plunder</hi> must be the only bonds to hold a little <hi>Remnant</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether from <hi>dissipation.</hi> No <hi>Venerable</hi> name of <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament</hi> is made a <hi>Stale</hi> to <hi>Countenance</hi> pernicious <hi>Councils,</hi> and <hi>acts of a close Committee.</hi> No <hi>Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tebanck</hi> of <hi>State</hi> by <hi>printed Papers</hi> which <hi>canting Tearms</hi> will <hi>cheat</hi> the <hi>Vulgar</hi> of their <hi>Coyn,</hi> and by <hi>unseasonable Purgings, Vomitings,</hi> and <hi>Blood letting,</hi> bring the whole <hi>Body Politick</hi> into an <hi>Atrophy,</hi> or <hi>Consumption;</hi> we need not fear a stranger <hi>Monster,</hi> who can survive the loss of an <hi>Head</hi> of the <hi>constitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of a <hi>Turkish Sheep,</hi> who <hi>runs all into Rump.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>How fortunate were our Countrey-men, could they be brought to understand their own Goods!</hi> And it was not a <hi>Misery</hi> intail'd on <hi>Mankind,</hi> to be made <hi>happy</hi> and <hi>blind</hi> at the same time. Some say we have a <hi>Golden Age</hi> already, while <hi>Gold</hi> is the <hi>price</hi> of <hi>all Things.</hi> An <hi>Asse</hi> mumbling upon <hi>Thistles</hi> thus
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:199216:15"/> laden, hath more <hi>Rhetorick</hi> then all <hi>Cicero's Orati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</hi> Some fear the <hi>Merchants</hi> will all turn <hi>Iews,</hi> since so many <hi>Iews</hi> are turn'd <hi>Merchants,</hi> that the <hi>Old Christian Faith</hi> will scarce pass upon the <hi>Exchange.</hi> The common <hi>City Geese</hi> gaggle, as if there was an <hi>Invasion</hi> of <hi>Gauls,</hi> &amp; the numerous <hi>French</hi> here wolud destroy the <hi>Capitol.</hi> The <hi>Grandee's</hi> hear ill for their <hi>Retinues</hi> of <hi>Forraigners,</hi> and the people cry out like the Ancient <hi>English Priests, Their Habitations are given to strangers.</hi> Or some are pleased to imagine them as <hi>stupid</hi> as <hi>Herodes Son,</hi> who had 24. Pages to learn him the Letters of the <hi>Alphabet.</hi> They can need no less number of <hi>French Lacquies</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member them of that <hi>Gibrish.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the Ingenious books of Mr. <hi>Roger L'estrange</hi> mind us of <hi>Paganism</hi> while he by his writings so much resembles a <hi>Primitive Christian,</hi> by <hi>Apologies, Caveat's, Modest pleas, Relaps'd Apostates,</hi> as if like a <hi>Father</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> he had not only to do with <hi>Heathens,</hi> but <hi>Hereticks.</hi> His books have as much <hi>Iuice</hi> as his <hi>Adversaries</hi> want, who by the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of it, run all into a <hi>Rind:</hi> Yet this <hi>Iuicy Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor</hi> dis-relishes on some <hi>palats,</hi> who to the <hi>Sweet Gobbets</hi> they have taken in, would not admit of any <hi>Sower Sauce.</hi> He is presum'd to be of no <hi>thri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Constitution,</hi> as not <hi>dappled</hi> betwixt <hi>Knave</hi> and <hi>Foole,</hi> the <hi>Italian Composition</hi> out of which is made up <hi>Preferment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I need not inform you when the <hi>Queen</hi> of <hi>Sweden</hi> last treated <hi>Embassadors,</hi> or the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Poland</hi> went a <hi>Hunting,</hi> or that <hi>his Holiness</hi> hath a <hi>Sore Toe,</hi> or a <hi>Great Cardinal</hi> a <hi>Cough,</hi> or how the <hi>Banditi</hi> rob in
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:199216:15"/>
               <hi>Italy,</hi> or the <hi>Lacquies</hi> in <hi>Paris.</hi> A <hi>Don</hi> is sick in <hi>Spain,</hi> a <hi>Marquess</hi> married in <hi>France.</hi> By the next you may hear of the <hi>Recovery</hi> of the one, or the <hi>Loss</hi> of the <hi>Mayden Fort</hi> by the <hi>Valour</hi> of the <hi>other,</hi> what effects this <hi>Sore Toe</hi> may have on <hi>Christendom,</hi> and what the <hi>Cardinal Coughs</hi> for; But I shall contract, least <hi>I</hi> may seem <hi>Probationer for the place</hi> of <hi>A States Scavenger,</hi> their <hi>Iakes Reformer,</hi> a <hi>Labour</hi> which might require another <hi>Hercules.</hi> I have gone <hi>beyond my last</hi> already, and may cry out with the unfortunate <hi>Wolf</hi> in the <hi>Fable,</hi> who <hi>gain'd</hi> nothing beside <hi>Stripes,</hi> for his <hi>services.</hi> I am no <hi>Preist?</hi> what need I sing Dirges's no Lawyer, what need I <hi>decide Controversies,</hi> no <hi>Chyrurgeon;</hi> What need I pretend to <hi>pluck out Thorns?</hi> yet, <hi>in the cause of God, the King, and Country</hi> as I heard that incomparable Lady, <hi>Isabel,</hi> late <hi>Countess of Northampton</hi> say) <hi>we must be content to do and suffer any thing.</hi> And in relation to my profession, I may be allow'd to <hi>State</hi> a <hi>Disease</hi> (though not to intermeddle with the diseases of State) and to <hi>prescribe,</hi> should it be (as many of our <hi>Profession</hi> do) without <hi>Knowledge,</hi> (since of all Diseases, ignorance is the most <hi>Epidemical</hi>) I may hope to be forgiven, though I can plead no privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge from my calling; while I render you by a <hi>tedious perusal</hi> a true <hi>Patient.</hi> You <hi>Sir</hi> cannot be affected with such <hi>Diseases,</hi> who supply no grosser <hi>Humor</hi> to swell (what K. <hi>Iames</hi> called) the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms <hi>Spleen</hi> by an un-necessary <hi>tumor,</hi> occasioning <hi>Leanness</hi> to the whole <hi>Body;</hi> His <hi>Majesty</hi> needs not fear from such <hi>Subjects</hi> (what his Royal Grand-Father did) to be made <hi>King</hi> of <hi>London</hi> only; The Tittle, additional lustre to a Court, not recompen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:199216:16"/> his <hi>dearness</hi> of <hi>Provision,</hi> the making their own <hi>Honors cheap,</hi> nor the loss of affection of his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects in the Countrey: while <hi>Owl</hi> and <hi>Bat</hi> were the only <hi>Countrey House keepers,</hi> and the howling of the Poor at a <hi>Mock Beggar-Hall,</hi> the only <hi>Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sick</hi> which attended the <hi>Nativity.</hi> You (Sir) Traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fick not in our <hi>Burse</hi> of <hi>Blasphemy</hi> and <hi>Ir-religion,</hi> take up no <hi>New fashioned Faith</hi> in <hi>Trust</hi> with Clothes; wear no <hi>Mannours</hi> on your <hi>back;</hi> have no <hi>stone</hi> in your <hi>Head;</hi> nor turn <hi>A City Alchymist</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting your Countrey <hi>Dirt</hi> into <hi>Gold,</hi> to furnish your pocket for a <hi>Gaming School;</hi> or to offer up to the <hi>she Calves</hi> of the <hi>Season;</hi> make no <hi>Inclosures</hi> at <hi>Home,</hi> to fence out the <hi>Poer,</hi> and lay all in <hi>waste</hi> at <hi>London,</hi> till you fall into worse <hi>Ditches</hi> then were digged for the ruin of others: and your <hi>Person</hi> as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well as <hi>Land</hi> may suffer an <hi>Inclosure.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I must forbear what is impertinent in respect of your Honoured self, and dangerous in relation to others. <hi>Mad men,</hi> not only menace, but (experience verifies) often hurt their <hi>Physitians.</hi> And should a <hi>Cure</hi> be effected on any of those <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naticks,</hi> who like the <hi>Mad man</hi> living at <hi>A Sea-Port,</hi> could suppose all the Riches of the Harbor his own, the Physitian might be only recompensed with curses by restoring those senses which may give no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of a <hi>Poverty,</hi> and hinder the benefits reaped from a deluded <hi>Imagination.</hi> Yet how inacceptable soever to others, I shall not appear ingrateful to you, who am as far as Virtue, Merit, Relation, Honor, can oblige</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
               <signed>Your most affectionately devoted Cozen, to serve you <hi>J. C.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:199216:16"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:199216:17"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:199216:17"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>